The first thing that you would do when you sign up on
أول شيء يجب فعله عند التسجيل على منصة عمل حر
a freelancing platform is to create a profile.
هو إنشاء ملف شخصي.
Now let's take a look at what a profile is.
الآن دعونا نلقي نظرة على المقصود بالملف الشخصي.
When a client publishes a task on a freelancing platform,
عندما ينشر العميل مهمة على منصة عمل حر
you as a freelancer,
أنت كموظف حر،
would send an expression of interest to the client to express your interest in this task.
سترسل رسالة إبداء اهتمام بالعمل لتوضيح رغبتك في العمل على المهمة.
But even before the client considers your expression of interest,
ولكن حتى قبل أن ينظر العميل لرسالة إبداء الاهتمام،
they may look at a profile on the platform, your profile.
فقد ينظر إلى ملفك الشخصي على المنصة، ملفك أنت.
Now profile is nothing but information about you.
والملف الشخصي ما هو إلا معلومات عنك.
A short bio about yourself,
فهو سيرة ذاتية مختصرة عن نفسك،
educational background, areas of expertise,
وعن خلفيتك التعليمية، ومجالات خبرتك،
and then relevant projects that you've worked on.
والمشاريع ذات الصلة التي عملت عليها سابقًا.
One might think that a profile is nothing but a resume of a freelancer.
قد يعتقد البعض أن الملف الشخصي ما هو إلا سيرة ذاتية للموظف الحر.
But profile is actually a little different from a resume
ولكن الملف الشخصي يختلف قليلًا عن السيرة الذاتية
that you would use to perhaps into companies to get full-time jobs.
التي قد تستخدمها للحصول على وظيفة بدوام كامل لدى الشركات.
Now let's look at what are the main differences between a profile and a resume.
الآن دعونا ننظر على الاختلافات الرئيسية بين الملف الشخصي والسيرة الذاتية.
First, a profile is much more brief and direct and it's
أولًا الملف الشخصي أكثر إيجازًا ومباشرة وهو
strong as compared to a resume which is more detailed and sophisticated.
أقوى عند مقارنته بالسيرة الذاتية التي قد تكون أكثر تفصيلًا وتعقيدًا.
But let's take an example to explain that point.
ولنأخذ مثالًا لشرح هذه النقطة.
If you have a skill of full-stack development,
إذا كان لديك مهارة فائقة في التطوير،
you may want the client to know what exactly you walk on and what's your core strength.
فقد تريد من العميل أن يعرف تحديدًا مسارات عملك ونقاط قوتك الأساسية.
In a freelancing profile,
في الملف الشخصي الخاص بالعمل الحر،
it's okay to say that you have mostly worked on
من الممكن أن تذكر أنك تستخدم غالبًا
Python and done some doublings in front-end technologies,
Python وعملت بعض التحسينات في تكنولوجيات الواجهات الأمامية،
which is not the kind of brevity and
ونحن لا نستعرض هذه التفاصيل
the language that you would use on a sophisticated resume.
ولا نستخدم هذه اللغة عند كتابة السيرة الذاتية المحترفة.
Second, a resume which is also used actively
ثانيًا: إن السيرة الذاتية التي تستخدم بفاعلية
for full-time jobs has many other details than your core work.
للحصول على وظائف الدوام الكامل تتضمن تفاصيل أخرى كثيرة غير أعمالك الأساسية.
It could talk about your co-curricular activities, for example,
يمكن أن تتحدث عن نشاطاتك، على سبيل المثال
like you are a black belt in karate,
أنك حصلت على الحزام الأسود في الكاراتيه،
or could talk about your volunteering experiences,
و يمكن أن تتحدث عن تجاربك التطوعية،
or even talk about your career objectives.
أو حتى تتحدث عن أهدافك المهنية.
Those details are generally not relevant in a freelancing profile.
وهذه التفاصيل غير ذات صلة عمومًا بملفك الشخصي على منصات العمل الحر.
The prime reason for that is that freelancing market is more direct and need-based.
والسبب الرئيسي هو أن منصات سوق العمل الحر أكثر مباشرة وقائمة على الاحتياجات.
Clients are only interested in seeing what you can do for them for their project at hand.
يهتم العملاء فقط برؤية ما يمكنك القيام به من أجل مشروعهم المطروح.
Whereas when applying for a full-time job using a resume,
في حين أنه عند تقديم طلب للحصول على وظيفة بدوام كامل باستخدام السيرة الذاتية،
a a company may also be interested in knowing about your soft skills,
تهتم الشركة أيضًا بمعرفة مهاراتك الشخصية،
other activities that you do, and so on.
أو أي أنشطة أخرى تقوم بها، وهكذا.
The third, which you might have guessed by now,
ثالثًا: وقد تكون بالفعل عرفته الآن،
is that freelancing profiles are less formal than resumes.
هو أن الملف الشخصي للعمل الحر أقل رسمية من السير الذاتية.
It's totally okay to say in your bio that you will not
فلا بأس أن تذكر في ملفك الشخصي أنك لن تتقاضى
charge if the client is not a 100 percent satisfied with your services,
أجر من العميل إن لم يكن 100% راضيًا عن الخدمة المُقدمة له
which is not something that you would put on a resume for sure.
ولكن لا تستطيع وضع ذلك في سيرتك الذاتية بالتأكيد.
In a nutshell, the client only wants to know if you can work on their task effectively.
باختصار العميل يريد فقط أن يعرف إن كنت تستطيع أن تؤدي المهمة بنجاح أم لا.
They're not interested if you're a runner or you run
لا يهتم العميل بمعرفة إن كنت تحب الجري أو إن
a YouTube channel on cooking with 100,000 subscribers,
كان لديك قناة طبخ على YouTube عليها 100.000 مشترك،
unless it's directly relevant to their work.
ما لم يكن لذلك علاقة بمهام العميل.
Now before getting into the different fields of a profile,
الآن، وقبل التطرق إلى خانات البيانات المختلفة في الملف الشخصي،
we will discuss some general best practices that will help you write a good profile.
سنناقش بعض أفضل الممارسات العامة التي ستساعدك في إعداد ملف شخصي قوي.
Remember that every freelancing platform will have
تذكر أن كل منصة من منصات العمل الحر لها
their own set of fields to fill in to create a freelancer's profile.
خانات بيانات مختلفة تستطيع استكمالها لإنشاء ملفك الشخصي للعمل الحر.
The first one is derived from the fact that clients
وهذا مستمد من واقع أن العملاء
are not reading your profile but skimming it.
يلقون نظرة سريعة فقط على ملفك.
Try to be as crisp and brief as possible,
حاول أن تكون واضح ومختصر قدر الإمكان،
highlighting your key strengths and experience.
سلط الضوء على نقاط قوتك وخبراتك.
This goes back to our mindset discussion on maximizing value for the client.
ويذكرنا ذلك بمناقشتنا السابقة عن تعظيم القيمة للعميل كأسلوب تفكير.
Try to hear the clients had and see what you would
حاول أن تضع نفسك مكان العميل وتخيل
look in a profile if you were hiring someone to do a task,
ماذا ستبحث عنه في ملف الموظف الذي تريد توظيفه للمهمة،
add those specific details.
وأضف هذه التفاصيل المحددة.
Now one mistake that freelancers often make is
هناك خطأ يقع فيه موظفي العمل الحر غالبًا وهو
just putting down a long list of the skills that they know.
إعداد قائمة طويلة بمهاراتهم.
In general, that is not a bad practice because
وبشكل عام، لا يعتبر هذا أسلوب سيئ حيث
the freelancing platforms encourage you to tag all your skills.
تشجعك منصة العمل الحر على ذكر جميع مهاراتك.
You can filter client requests based on the skills that you have put in your profile.
يمكنك انتقاء طلبات العميل بناء على المهارات التي وضعتها في ملفك الشخصي.
But it is important to also call out your core expertise in your profile.
ولكن من المهم أيضًا أن تشير إلى خبراتك الأساسية في ملفك الشخصي.
For example, it's okay to mention that you know PHP,
على سبيل المثال: لا بأس من ذكر أنك تعرف PHP،
Python [inaudible] Bootstrap, and React.
Python [inaudible] Bootstrap، وReact.
But it's good to mention your core strengths.
لكن من الجيد ذكر نقاط قوتك الأساسية.
This will help the client know what is really
هذا سيساعد العميل على معرفة مجال
your deep skill and what you can work on with little exploration if needed.
قوتك، وما يمكنك العمل عليه مع القليل من الاستكشاف إذا لزم الأمر.
Lastly, nothing better for a client to be able to see your work done in the past.
وأخيرًا، فإن أفضل شيء للعميل هو أن يرى إنجازاتك السابقة.
This will help the client relate your past work with
هذا سيساعد العميل على الربط بين أعمالك السابقة
their project and help them assess whether you are a good fit.
ومشروعهم الحالي، وبذلك يحدد العميل إذا كنت الشخص الملائم للوظيفة أم لا.
If you have links to your past work that is not predicted
تستطيع مشاركة عملك السابق،
by a non-disclosure agreement and is available publicly,
في حال لم يكن هناك اتفاق سرية وعدم إفصاح،
do share them in your profile.
فإن كان الأمر ممكنًا شارك أعمالك في ملفك الشخصي.